A Guide to the Echols family papers, 1818-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Echols family papers, 1818-1999
The Library of Virginia
52127
2.86 cu. ft. and 7 boxes
Echols family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Porter and June Echols of Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Ernest Echols (1864-1926) was the son of Edward Echols (1817-1874) and his second wife Susan Hobson Burks Echols (1834-1870) of Rockbridge County, Virginia. Ernest Echols operated Big Bend Coal Company in Fayette County, West Virginia, while living in both Fayette County and Rockbridge County. He married Nannie Morton Carter (1864-1923) in Fayette County on 28 April 1890, and they had nine children, including Porter Burks Echols (1902-1990) who became a physician in Rockbridge County and Lynchburg, Virginia. He married Hortense Crum Reynolds (1904-1982) of Bedford, Iowa, on 10 January 1931. Their son, Porter Burks Echols, Jr., also became a physician. He married Nila June Welsh 14 July 1956.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1818-1999, of the Echols family of Rockbridge County and Lynchburg, Virginia, and Fayette County, West Virginia, consisting of accounts, advertisements, calling cards, catalogs, checks, correspondence, deeds, genealogical notes, photographs, receipts, tax records, and other papers detailing the family's personal and business interests, including their activities in the coal industry, retail, and medical profession. Also contains correspondence and papers relating to Ernest Echols' sons' education at the Virginia Military Institute. Also includes genealogical information on the Echols family and the Logue family, including photographs, and information on property owned by the Echols family. Papers also include clippings and articles on general subjects relating to the Echols family and to Rockbridge County.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Correspondence and papers, 1903-1999
Series II: Family genealogy
Series III: Land records
Series IV: Business records, 1818-1919
Series V: General subjectsSeries VI: Hortense Reynolds scrapbook and yearbooks.
Series VI: Hortense Reynolds scrapbook and yearbooks
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence and papers, 1903-1999., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Series I: Correspondence and papers, 1903-1999, consists of accounts, advertisements, calling cards, catalogs, clippings, correspondence, deeds, receipts, scrapbooks, tax records, yearbooks, and other papers of Ernest Echols (1864-1926) of Rockbridge County, Virginia, and Fayette County, West Virginia, highlighting his business interests in coal mines, including the Big Bend Coal Company, as well as in stores. Includes correspondence from family members discussing family and business matters. Papers also contains correspondence from Ernest Echols' sons while enrolled at the Virginia Military Institute, as well as grades, receipts, checks, and other papers. Also includes a copy of "Some Echols Family Letters" consisting of correspondence between Eliza F. Echols (1795-1875), her son Edward Echols (1817-1874), and his son John Jordan Echols (1846-1926) all of Rockbridge County and Greenbrier and Monroe Counties, West Virginia.
  - Correspondence and papers, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and papers, January-April 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and papers, September-December 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and papers, February-june 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and papers, August 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and papers, September-October 1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and papers, November-December 1908 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and papers, February-June 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and papers, July-December 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and papers, March-July 1911 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and papers, August-December 1911 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence and papers, January-July 1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and papers, August-December 1914 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence and papers, January-June 1915 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence and papers, January-November 1915 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and papers, January-October 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and papers, November-December, no date 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1927, 1930, 1931, 1935, 1947, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1909-1915 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence, 1916-1918 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Checks to Ernest C., Frank, Charles L., Joseph, and Ralph Echols, 1907, 1911-1918 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Checks to the Virginia Military Institute for Ernest C., Frank, Charles L., Joseph, and Ralph Echols, 1910-1918 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Military Institute receipts, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - J. Ed. Deavers receipts for VMI uniforms, etc., 1910-1918 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Checks to J. Ed. Deavers and others, 1910-1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Some Echols Letters, 1858-1904, pp. 1-50 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Some Echols Letters, 1858-1904, pp. 51-100 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Some Echols Letters, 1858-1904, pp. 101-150 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Some Echols Letters, 1858-1904, pp. 151-195 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series II: Family genealogy., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Series II: Family genealogy contains notes, photographs, and records on the Echols family genealogy. Also contains genealogical information and photogoraphs of the Logue and Welsh families of Ohio, the family of Jane Welsh Echols, wife of Porter Echols, Jr. Includes biographical information on Confederate general John W. Echols (1823-1896).
  - Echols family genealogical notes (pink notebook) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Echols family genealogical notes (red notebook) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Papers relating to Echols family genealogy (folder 1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Papers relating to Echols family genealogy (folder 2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Papers relating to Echols family genealogy (folder 3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Logue family genealogy (folder 1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Logue family genealogy (folder 2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Echols family photographs (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Echols family photographs (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Logue-Welsh family photographs (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John W. Echols article and related materials (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III: Land records., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4 (folders 1-7))
  Series III: Land records includes deeds of sale for property owned by members of the Echols family. Contains deed, 12 May 1949, for Echols Farm and a nomination, 1998, for the Echols Farm to be included in the National Register of Historic Places, as well as other papers concerning the Echols Farm.
  - National Society Daughters of the American Revolution Project--Echols family deeds (folder 1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Society Daughters of the American Revolution Project--Echols family deeds (folder 2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Deed--Echols Farm, 12 May 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Echols Farm National Registration Nomination, July 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Echols Farm National Registration Nomination, (copy) July 1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Papers relating to Echols Farm (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings on Echols family and Echols family houses (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Business records, 1818-1919., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4 (folders 8-16))
  Series IV: Business records includes bills and correspondence, 1905-1919, of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad; correspondence and receipts, 1906-1917, from Modern Woodmen of America; checks, 1911-1917, drawn on the Bank of Glasgow and on the People's Bank in Buena Vista, Virginia. Also includes pages from an unidentified account book, 1818, from Richmond, Virginia, containing accounts for Moses Echols; and an unidentified account book, 1885-1894, from near Lynchburg, Virginia.
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad papers, 1905-1919, no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Modern Woodmen of America papers (Camp 7608, Fayette County, West Virginia), 1906-1909 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Modern Woodmen of America papers (Camp 7608, Camp 12460, Fayette County, West Virginia; Camp 15524, Buena Vista, Virginia), 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Modern Woodmen of America papers (Camp 15524, Buena Vista, Virginia; Camp 12832, Rockbridge County, Virginia), 1913-1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bank of Glasgow (Rockbridge County, Virginia) checks, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bank of Glasgow (Rockbridge County, Virginia) checks, 1914-1916 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bank of Glasgow (Rockbridge County, Virginia) checks, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The People's Bank (Buena Vista, Virginia) checks, 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Account and account books 1818, 1885-1894 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series V: General subjects., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4 (folders 17-23))
  General subjects includes clippings, programs, and other papers relating to the Echols family and the history of Rockbridge County, including articles on a monument to Frank Padgett (d. 1854) an enslaved African American who led a rescue effort of people involved in a boat accident along the James and North (Maury) Rivers.
  - Washington and Lee alumni (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - University of Richmond inauguration of 7th president, 18 March 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pages from A History of Rockbridge County (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Clippings on the Civil War (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Clippings on history (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Clippings on the James River and the James River and Kanawha Canal (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Clippings on monument to Frank Padgett, 1968-1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series VI: Hortense Crum Reynolds scrapbook and yearbooks, 1920-1922., Extent: 2 box. (Box 5-6)
  Series VI: Hortense Reynolds scrapbook and yearbooks contains Hortense Crum Reynolds' (Echols) (1904-1982) yearbooks from Bedford High School (Bedford, Iowa) (1920) and Ward-Belmont School (Nashville, Tennessee) (1921-1922), and a scrapbook from Ward-Belmont.
  - Purple and White, Bedford High School (Bedford, Iowa) yearbook, 1920 (Box 5)
  - English word definitions and photo album pages found in Purple and White, Bedford High School (Bedford, Iowa) yearbook, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Milestones, Ward-Belmont School (Nashville, Tennessee) yearbook, 1921 (Box 5)
  - Milestones, Ward-Belmont School (Nashville, Tennessee) yearbook, 1922 (Box 5)
  - Ward-Belmont School (Nashville, Tennessee) scrapbook, 1921-1922 (Box 6)
- Oversize materials., Extent: 1 box. (Box 7)
  Contains oversize materials from Series I: Correspondence and papers and from Series IV: Business records.
  - Record of loading for New River District, 10 April 1907 (from box 1, folder 5) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dixie Lumber Company letter and bills, 3 June 1915 (from box 1, folder 20) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dixie Lumber Company account, 26 September 1915 (from box 1, folder 21) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Individual income tax return for calendar year, 1917 (from box 2, folder 3) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Moses Echols accounts from Richmond merchant account book, February-December 1818 (from box 4, folder 16) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Account book, unidentified merchant, probably Lynchburg, 1885-1894 (from box 4, folder 16) (Box 7, Folder 6)